Apoorv Umang Saxena

Website: apoorvumang.github.io Email: apoorvsaxena@iisc.ac.in apoorvumang@gmail.com **?**: github.com/apoorvumang

Phone: +91 7891947877

Research Interests

I am broadly interested in machine learning, natural language processing and related fields. In my post-graduate work, I have had a specific focus on knowledge graphs (KG) and question answering. In this area, I have tried to improve QA performance by combining pre-trained language models with KG embeddings. I have also worked on making KG embeddings scalable and easier to apply to downstream tasks through the use of unified sequence-to-sequence models. During my undergraduate studies I worked on the Government of India sponsored project "Acyut" which was India's first humanoid robot.

EDUCATION

Indian Institute of Science

Bangalore

Ph.D., Computational and Data Sciences. Advisor: Prof. Partha Talukdar

2018-Present

Birla Institute of Technology and Science (BITS), Pilani

Pilani

B.E. (Hons.) Computer Science, Grade: 8.6

2011 - 2015

EXPERIENCE

IBM Research Bangalore Research Intern Summer 2019

- As part of NLG group, I worked on the problem to generate natural language highlights from structured data
- Used table-to-text techniques to generate automatic summaries of match scorecards and weather reports

Google Hyderabad

May 2016-March 2017 Software Engineer 3

- I worked in the Apps for Work team (now re-branded as Google Workspace) as Software Engineer (Tools & Infrastructure) for the Permissions Management mobile app
- Developed and maintained automation tools to increase tester productivity and reduce turnaround time

Pavpal Chennai

Software Engineer 1

July 2015-November 2015

- As part of the Reporting team at PayPal, I worked on migrating mid-tier Java services to a new framework
- My work here involved working with Java Enterprise Edition and PayPal's relational databases

Flipkart Bangalore

PS 2 Intern January 2015-June 2015

- Worked in the E-kart team at Flipkart and developed the UI for a Master Data Management system
- The UI was developed using Angular and Node.js framework and deployed in production

Bhabha Atomic Research Centre

Mumbai

Summer Intern Summer 2013

- Did a chemical analysis project titled "Ascertaining bubble size distribution in immiscible liquid flows"
- Developed image processing techniques to measure bubble size distribution and their generation frequency

PUBLICATIONS

- 1. A. Saxena, A. Kochsiek, and R. Gemulla, "Sequence-to-Sequence Knowledge Graph Completion and Question Answering", Accepted to the 60th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 2022.
- 2. A. Saxena, S. Chakrabarti, and P. Talukdar, "Question Answering Over Temporal Knowledge Graphs", Proceedings of the 59th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 2021. QC
- 3. A. Saxena, A. Tripathi, and P. Talukdar, "Improving Multi-hop Question Answering over Knowledge Graphs using Knowledge Base Embeddings", Proceedings of the 58th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 2020. QC
- 4. A. Gautam, A. U. Saxena, P. Mall, and S. Mohan, "Positioning multiple mobile robots for geometric pattern formation: An empirical analysis", Seventh International Conference on Contemporary Computing (IC3), 2014

SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

• Recipient of Intel India PhD Fellowship	2018-Present
\bullet Represented India and stood 4th in Teen-size league at Robocup 2013 held in the Netherlands	2013
• 1st runner-up in image processing and robotics events at Techfest 2013 and 2014, IIT Bombay	2013-2014
- 1st position in Desert Hack 2012, BITS Pilani, for application Kiri ${\overline{\pmb{C}}}$	2012
- Awarded BITS merit scholarship for semesters 1-4 for being in the top 1% of current batch	2011-2013
• Secured rank 2,423 in IIT-JEE (top 0.49%), rank 301 in AIEEE (top 0.05%)	2011

Positions of Responsibility

$\bullet~$ TA for course DS-226 "Introduction to Computing for AI and ML" at IISc Bangalore	2021
• Reviewer at AKBC 2021, ACL 2021, ACL Rolling Review	2020-Present
• Co-founded Embedded Systems & Robotics Laboratory, BITS Pilani	2014
• Lead of computer vision, Team Acyut (robotics club) at BITS Pilani	2012-2013

Extracurricular Projects

• Humanoid Robot Soccer 2 2011–2015 Member of team Acyut, which is a humanoid robotics project sponsored by Department of Electronics and Information Technology, Government of India. Represented India in Robocup 2013.

• Swarm Robotics - Implementing testbed using e-puck robots 2014–2015 Project for testing swarm algorithms and validating simulation results. Tested some solutions to the circle formation problem on a hardware testbed. The work led to a paper that was published in the IC3 2014.

• Pediatric Practice Management Solution 2012-Present Wrote an open source PHP solution for pediatric practice management that has been in active use since 2013.

SKILLS

- Machine Learning Tools: PyTorch, Tensorflow, Keras
- **Programming:** Production level code in C, C++ and Java.
- Web Development: Angular, Node, HTML, PHP
- Hardware: AVR Microcontrollers, Arduino boards, Raspberry Pi
- Design Software: Adobe Photoshop, Autodesk Fusion 360